Register of the Lauchlin Bernard Currie papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lauchlin Bernard Currie papers
1941-1993
80013
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (2.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, and summaries of interviews relating to American aid to China during World War II, conditions in China, and military operations in the China-Burma-India Theater. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Currie, Lauchlan Bernard.
Access
Collection open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1902 October 8 Born, Nova Scotia, Canada
1925 B.S., London University
1931 Ph.D., Harvard University
1929-1934 Instructor, Harvard University
1932-1934 Professor, Fletcher Graduate School
1934 Economist, U.S. Treasury
1934 Author, The Supply and Control of Money
1935-1939 Asst. Director Research, Federal Reserve Board
1939-1945 Administrative Assistant to President Franklin D. Roosevelt
1940-1941 Director, Lend-Lease for China
1942 Personal Representative of President Roosevelt to China
1943-1944 Deputy Director, Foreign Economic Administration
1945-1949 President, Lauchlin Currie and Company, New York
1949-1950 Director, International Bank Mission to Colombia
1950-1951 Adviser and Director, Comite de Desarrollo Economico, Colombia
1951-1953 Adviser, Colombian Planning Committee, 1951-1953
1953-1959 In retirement
1959 Director, Robert Nathan Magadalena Valley Study
1961-1967 Director, Fundación para el Progreso de Colómbia
1965 Editor and co-author, Una Política Urbana para un País en Desarrollo
1965 Author, Plan Socio-Económico para el Atlantico
1965 Professor of Economics, National University of Colombia
1965 Visiting Professor, Michigan State University
1966 Author, Accelerating Development
1966 Royer Lecturer, University of California, Berkeley
1966-1967 Director and Professor, Department of Economics, National University, Colombia
1966-1967 Director, Center of Development Research, National University, Colombia
1967 Co-author, Governmental Planning and Political Economy
1967-1968 Visiting Professor, Simon Fraser University, Canada
1968 Author, Obstacles to Development
1968-1969 Visiting Professor, Glasgow University
1969-1971 Professor, Simon Fraser University, Canada
1971-1976 Adviser, National Planning Agency, Colombia
1972-1974 Member, Board of Savings and Housing, Colombia
1974 Author, Ahorro, Correccion Monetaria y Construccion
1974-1976 Consultant to the United Nations on Urban Matters
1976 Author, Taming the Megalopolis: A Design for Urban Growth
1976- Member of Board of Directors, Instituto de Estudios Colombianos
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China.; Lend-lease operations (1941-1945); United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; United States--Foreign relations.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Correspondence, 1941-1950
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Bond, W. L., 1941 (Box 1)
  - Brainard, Rear Admiral Roland M., 1941
  - Carpenter, S.R., 1941
  - Chang, Carsun, 1941
  - Chennault, General Claire L., (code name - Groco), 1941-1942
  - Chiang Kai-shek, 1941
  - Chiang Kai-shek, Mme., 1941-1943
  - Chiang Kai-shek and Chiang Kai-shek, Mme., (code name - Segac), 1941-1942
  - Chien, C. C., 1941
  - Chih Tsang, 1942
  - Churchill, Winston, 1942
  - Davies, John Paton, 1942
  - Donovan, William J., 1942
  - Eccles, Marriner S., 1941
  - Fortas, Abe, 1950
  - Greene, Robert S., 1941-1943
  - Holbrook, Major Lucius R., 1942-1943
  - Hopkins, Harry, 1941-1943
  - Howe, C. D., 1941
  - Keating, John G., 1941
  - Kung, H. H., 1941-1944
  - Li Ming, 1945
  - Little, L. K., 1943-1945
  - Liu Chieh, 1942
  - Luce, Henry R., 1942
  - McCammon, Colonel J. E., 1942
  - McHugh, Colonel J. M., 1941-1945
  - Magruder, Brigadier General John, 1942
  - Marshall, General George C., 1942
  - Messersmith, George S., 1941
  - Meyberg, Manfred, 1942
  - Morganthau, Henry, Jr., 1942-1943
  - People's Political Council, 1941
  - Price, Frank W., 1941-1942
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1943
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1941-1942
  - Sayre, Francis B., 1941
  - Smith, General Walter Bedell, 1942
  - Soong, T. V., 1941-1942
  - Stilwell, General Joseph, 1942
  - Stimson, Henry L., 1942
  - Thompson, Malvina, 1942
  - Tong, Hollington, 1941-1945
  - Tully, Grace, 1942-1943
  - Vincent, John Carter, 1941-1943
  - Walsh, R. J., 1942
  - Wang Shih-chieh, 1941
  - Wei Tao-ming, 1945
  - Welles, Sumner, 1941-1943
  - Wheeler, General R. A., 1941-1943
  - Wong Wen-hao, 1941-1976
- Subject File, 1940-1976
  Memoranda, reports correspondence, notes, and printed material, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Volunteer Group (AVG) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and memoranda
      - 1940 January - 1941 April
      - 1941 May-September
      - 1941 October
      - 1941 November
      - 1941 December
      - 1942 January-March
      - 1942 April-May
      - 1942 June-July 1942
      - 1942 September - 1943 September
    - Reports
      - "History and Status of the First American Volunteer Group," Toungoo, Burma, 1941 October 19
      - "Notes on Strategic Possibilities of A Small American Air Force in China"
  - Burma
  - Burma Road
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1941 August - 1942 January
    - Reports
      - "Present Trucking Operations as Conducted on the Burma Road and Recommendations for Their Improvement," by Daniel G. Arnstein, Harold C. Davis, and Marco F. Hellman, 1941 August 9
      - "Some Observations and Impressions on the Yunnan-Burma Transportation Situation,", undated
      - Yui Fei-pang, Chairman of the Yunnan-Burma Highway, Report 1 and Report 2, 1941 June 16, June 17
  - Canada - Foreign relations (Box 3)
  - Chang Kia-ngau - Notes on conference, 1941 February 21
  - Chen Pao-chuang - Notes on conference, 1941 February 14
  - Chennault, General Claire L. - Memoranda, 1942 August
  - Chiang Kai-shek
    - Biographical notes
    - Correspondence
      - Churchill, Winston, 1941
      - Lo Ying-ching, 1942
      - Roosevelt, President Franklin D., 1941-1942
      - Soong, T. V., 1941-1942
      - Stilwell, General Joseph, 1942
    - Memoranda
      - To Lauchlin Currie (2), 1941 February 26 and undated
      - To Franklin Roosevelt (2), 1942 July 30, August 6
    - Report by Lauchlin Currie for Chiang Kai-shek
    - Speeches and writings
      - China's Destiny
        - Summary translation
        - Comments on the book by two American observers in China
      - "Impressions of My Visit to India and Observations on the War Situation in the Pacific," address delivered at memorial service, 1942 March 9
      - Speech to Kuomintang leaders, 1941 March 24
  - Chiang Kai-shek, Mme.
  - Ch'ien, T. S., excerpt from letter, 1941 August
  - China
    - Communists
    - Economic conditions
      - General
      - Banknotes
      - Correspondence, 1941-1942
      - Currency
      - Exchange
      - Gold
      - Loans
      - Rural economy
      - State monopolies
      - Trade
    - Labor
    - Military
    - Politics and government
  - Chinese Exclusion Act (Box 4)
  - Chinese Flying Cadets - Training in U.S.
  - Chinese Industrial Cooperatives
  - Chou En-lai (see Currie, Lauchlin - First Trip to China, - Chiang Kai-shek - Interviews), 1941 February
  - Clark-Kerr, Sir Archibald - Notes on conference, 1941 February 8
  - Cooper, Meriam - Notes on conversation, 1942 December 29
  - Currie, Lauchlin
    - First trip to China, 1941 February
      - Awards - Decoration of the Order of Ching Hsin, 1947 February 19
      - Expense report
      - Interviews with Chiang Kai-shek, and compiled notes on interviews, (latter includes notes on interview with Chou En-lai), 1941
      - Notes
      - Plans and letters of introduction
      - Press clippings
      - Report by American Ambassador Nelson Johnson, 1941 March 3
      - Report by Lauchlin Currie to President Roosevelt, 1941 March 15
    - Second trip to China, 1942 July - August
      - Conference notes
      - Interviews with Chiang Kai-shek, 1942
      - Miscellaneous
      - Notes
      - Plans
      - Press clippings
      - Report by Lauchlin Currie to President Roosevelt, 1942 August 24
      - Travel arrangements and expense
  - Davies, John Paton - "The China-Burma-India Theater - a Reappraisal,", 1942 July 31
  - Eisenhower, President Dwight D. - Memoranda, copy of letter, 1942
  - Fairbank, John K. - Memorandum on Air Program for China, (attached note by Lauchlin Currie 1942), memoranda, 1944 (Box 5)
  - Flying Tigers (see American Volunteer Group)
  - Freeman, Fulton? - Conference on situation in China, 1941 February
  - Ho Ying-chin - Conference, 1941 February 17
  - Hopkins, Harry - Memoranda, 1941 August-September
  - Hsu Yung-chang - Notes on conversation, 1941 February 20
  - Hull, Cordell - Notes and memoranda, 1941 April-May, 1942 September
  - International business enterprises, 1944 January
  - Jones, Joseph - Memoranda, 1941 April-May
  - Koo, Y. C. - Notes on conference, 1941 February 13
  - Kung, H. H. - Notes on conference, letter from Henry Luce, letter to Franklin Roosevelt, 1941-1942, 1944
  - Lattimore, Owen (code name - Omita)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1942
    - Meeting notes, 1942 December 4
    - Memoranda on appointment as political adviser to Chiang Kai-shek, 1941 May-June
  - LeHand, Miss - Memorandum, 1941 March 16
  - Liu Wei-chang - Notes on conversation, 1941 February 25
  - Lo Ying-ching - Report to Chiang Kai-shek., 1942 June 25
  - Luce, Henry - Memorandum on Luce, 1942 November 10
  - Lynch, - Notes on conference, 1941 February 14
  - Magruder, Brigadier General John. Holograph report by Lauchlin Currie entitled "The Magruder Mission,", undated
  - Marshall, General George C. - notes on interview, memorandum from Lieutenant General Brehon Somervell, 1942
  - Pai Chung-hsi - Notes on conversation, 1941 February
  - Philippine Islands - Letter to Department of State from Laurence Salisbury, 1940 December 13
  - Price, Harry B. - Memorandum on "China's Economic Needs and American Aid,", 1941 February 19
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor - Memoranda (2), 1942 September 16 and undated
  - Roosevelt, President Franklin D.
    - Meeting notes, 1942 June 26
    - Memoranda, 1941-1944
  - Roy, Andrew T. - Notes on conference, 1941 February
  - Schaberg, Benjamin F., Jr. - Memorandum on "Russia as a Source of Supply for China,", 1942 September 4
  - Stein, Gunther - Notes on conference, 1941 February
  - "Situation in China Since Stilwell's Recall," (carbon of article by Newsweek correspondent Harold Isaacs), 1942 December 22
  - Somervell, Lieutenant General Brehon - Memorandum for General Clay, 1942 August 29
  - Soong, T. V. - Memorandum for Franklin Roosevelt, newspaper clipping about Soong; notes on Soong, 1941-1944
  - Stilwell, General Joseph - Memoranda, notes; proposed message, holograph and typewritten memorandum by Stilwell entitled, "General View of the Situation,", 1942 and undated
  - Stimson, Henry - Memorandum, 1941 April 22
  - Sun Fo - Notes on conference, 1941 January 18
  - Sun Yat-sen, Mme. - proposed trip to the United States
  - Tong, Hollington - excerpts from memoranda, notes on Tong, 1941, 1943
  - United China Relief
  - United States
    - Department of the Treasury
    - Economic assistance - China
    - Foreign relations
      - Canada
      - Russia
    - Military assistance - China
    - War Production Board, 1944
  - Watson, General Edwin M.? - Memorandum, 1942 February 11
  - Wei Tao-ming - Biography; seating arrangement at Chinese Ambassador's dinner, 1942 October 21
  - Welles, Sumner - Memoranda, 1941-1942
  - Wheeler, Major General R. A. - Memorandum for General Stilwell on "Monthly Shipping Tonnage Required from United States to Supply One Triangular Division in India,", 1942 August 11
  - White, Theodore - Dispatch from Loyang, (also correspondence received by Lauchlin Currie about dispatch), 1943 March 13
  - Willauer, Whiting - notes on conversation, 1942 June 4
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - General
    - Pacific theater
  - Wu, K. C. - Notes on conference, 1941 February 15
- Photographs, circa 1942 (Envelope A)
  16 prints (some duplicates) of bombing of Haiphong, French Indo-China (Vietnam) August 9, 1942(?)
- 1985 October Increment, 1943 May 18 (Box 5)
  Photocopy of a memorandum for the president written by L. Currie relating to the situation in China and to U.S. foreign policy vis-a-vis that country.
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1941, 1945
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Available as PDF files. The PDF files are page images, so full-text search is not possible. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by date of creation.
  - 2010 release of records, 1945 (Reading room Workstation)
  - 2017 release of records, 1941 (Reading room Workstation)